<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-07T03:24:52+00:00</updated><id>https://salmanismustafa.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Salman Mustafa</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Truth Bomb</title><link href="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/truthBomb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Truth Bomb"/><published>2024-05-06T22:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-06T22:51:00+00:00</updated><id>https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/truthBomb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/truthBomb/"><![CDATA[<p>Truth Bomb</p> <p>I’m writing this as a way of holding myself accountable. I know I can live a richer, more fulfilled, better life. It is what I do every day that maketh the man. I am aware of this. Yet I go on living each day, in no particular hurry, doing the same shit that I know won’t take me where I want to go.</p> <p>Where do you want to go? To the land of achievement. Achievement of what? Achievement of the things I find worthy. What do you find worthy?</p> <p>The fit physique. The calm mind. The chunky checking and swollen savings accounts. The healthy relationships. The diverse hobbies. The contentment. The feeling of having brought goodness into the world. The feeling of having lived life well.</p> <p>These truth bombs are written and designed from my perspective. They are written in an effort to awaken me from the spiritual and psychological stasis I’ve fallen into over the years. I hope the brutal sledgehammer of hard facts is sufficient to put me on a path toward a more meaningful life. And,</p> <p>I hope some of these are of value to you. Thank you for being here.</p> <p>Love,</p> <p>Me</p> <p>I</p> <p>You spend too much time on your phone. What are you even doing there? Looking at pictures of people fitter and richer than you. Finding amusement in the humiliation of others. Reading about other people’s opinions on things. Have your own. The internet is vast, nigh endless. Use it wisely. There is much to be learned, but there is also much bullshit. Do you know what there isn’t that much of?</p> <p>Time</p> <p>II</p> <p>You give up on things too easily. When something takes effort, there is infinite potential for improvement. Things are difficult before they become easy.</p> <p>Your resilience in the face of difficulty (the measure of how much you’re willing to suck at something before getting good), determines how far you are willing to go to achieve the things you desire.</p> <p>Don’t be a quitter. Quitters never win and winners never quit.</p> <p>III</p> <p>You’re inauthentic. A life of conformity made you docile. You bite your tongue out of fear of confrontation. Be honest with people. It is owed to them and to yourself.</p> <p>Personal and professional relationships only survive through honesty. Nobody wants to be friends with a fake. Nobody is truly friends with someone that agrees with them all the time.</p> <p>Listen well. Speak with confidence and conviction. Make eye contact. Be gracious and gentle. Be firm and unwavering.</p> <p>IV</p> <p>Mind your posture. Stretch in the morning to feel comfortable in your skin. The human body is a marvel of evolutionary engineering. Some basic maintenance can go a long way in improving longevity and quality of function.</p> <p>Stay sufficiently hydrated and eat nourishing foods. Don’t be afraid to try new things. There are a plethora of flavors and textures to be discovered. Different nutrients have different effects on your biochemistry. Don’t fall into a routine of eating the same shit every single day. You would be doing a disservice to your body and depriving yourself of the deep emotional impact good food can have.</p> <p>Exercise to look and feel good. Make it fun. Humans have a natural tendency towards movement that’s slowly been unlearned over the course of modernity. Play sports. Walk in new places. Swim. Lift heavy things. Physical exertion is good for your brain.</p> <p>The sedentary life, in my experience, leads to bouts of depression, causes discontentment, and disrupts the natural rhythm and flow of life.</p> <p>Sleep well. Rest is crucial to optimal performance. Your batteries need recharging. You’re a better person when you’re well rested.</p> <p>V</p> <p>Other people’s successes make you insecure. That’s not a healthy reaction to your peers moving up in life. Feel genuinely happy for someone who has worked themselves into a better standing. If what they’ve achieved is something you want for yourself, use their success as motivation.</p> <p>It is easy to pity someone. It often doesn’t challenge your sense of self worth. But seeing others work to achieve dreams that look like yours? That makes you question what you’ve been doing. This can be discomforting. Use it as fuel to put in the effort to bring your dream to life.</p> <p>Speak encouragingly. Don’t diminish your successes nor failures. The journey is incomplete without both. Learn from them. Share the experience.</p> <p>VI</p> <p>Call your friends. Even if there’s nothing to talk about. Especially if there’s nothing to talk about. Ask what they’ve been doing lately. More importantly, ask how they’ve been feeling lately.</p> <p>The world is becoming increasingly isolated. You only share what you think are the greatest things about yourself. You don’t bring up ugly truths that keep you up at night. You feel vulnerable sharing your insecurities.</p> <p>Though it may be difficult initially to open up about them, it is freeing to be honest about your insecurities. Your friends won’t judge you. They will, in fact, admire your candor.</p> <p>Give people their flowers while they’re still around. Don’t be afraid to tell them you love them, respect them and appreciate all that they bring to the table.</p> <p>VII</p> <p>You can be kind of an ingrate. Take stock of your blessings. Life is the collective of moments we live through from birth until death. Some of them are glorious, rich and so utterly pleasurable. Some of them are quite shit. We can’t do without either.</p> <p>Practice gratitude. Feel your joys fully and accept your pain as part of the process.</p> <p>Be passionate about life every day. Seize each moment and live it purposefully. Life isn’t promised to anyone. Our time on this planet is fleeting, but it can be fulfilling if spent wisely. Make time for the things that bring you joy. Make time to make an effort towards goals you find worthy.</p> <p>Be grateful for life’s gifts. Be grateful for the infinite possibilities of life. Be grateful for free will.</p> <p>VIII</p> <p>You used to think Free Will was bullshit. You still kinda do. But the psychological effect of thinking your choices have an impact on the course of your own life is immense.</p> <p>Be cognizant of your choices. Try to focus on the forces that drive and sway them. See how your choices affect others, the world, yourself.</p> <p>Explore different styles of living. Try not to do what everybody else is. This is the easiest option, but in the long run, the least fulfilling. Choose wisely.</p> <p>IX</p> <p>Be a generous lover. Listen to your partner and remember the things they confide in you. Show them you remembered with little gestures of affection, gifts, notes and surprises.</p> <p>Be worthy of their love. Communicate thoughtfully and deeply. Learn what they like and show interest in their passions. The world looks beautiful through their eyes. Empathize with them and be the person they need you to be in times of joy and sorrow.</p> <p>Tell them your secrets. Trust them with your heart. Make them feel like they have someone in this world.</p> <p>X</p> <p>You’re unforgiving. You judge people by their actions and yourself by your intentions. You’ve done things that people have needed to forgive you for. Understand that everyone has history. Their journeys are filled with depths and events you most likely will never fully understand. Give people the benefit of the doubt.</p> <p>Forgive easily. Forgive people for their transgressions, and you will be quicker to forgive yourself. Holding a grudge never did anyone any good.</p> <p>It isn’t easy to forgive when you’ve been wronged. But it is the best thing you can do for yourself when it happens.</p> <p>You are deeply cynical. Skeptical of people’s intentions, you find them untrustworthy. Not everyone is out to get you. Most people aren’t peddling lies and trying to deceive.</p> <p>Healthy skepticism is fine. Don’t take someone’s word for anything. Do your due diligence. But don’t be a cynical bastard. Don’t see the worst in people.</p> <p>Allow people to earn your trust. Let your word be your bond. Speak to convey your mind, not convince someone of its validity.</p> <p>XI</p> <p>You don’t know what moves you. Or at the very least are confused about your preferences. Be aware of your taste. Know what you like and dislike and be conscious of how different things make you feel.</p> <p>The world as we know it is abundant with options. From food to film, music, pastimes, careers, friends, partners, places to live and visit. Choices are unlimited. Choose wisely.</p> <p>Be prudent of what drives your choices. We do not act in a vacuum. All of your tastes are defined by what you’ve known. Do your best to understand why you prefer one thing over another.</p> <p>XII</p> <p>Your mind often wanders. You cannot control the torrent of thoughts hurtling through your brain and information overload only shortens your attention span.</p> <p>Take stock of your thoughts. Give each one its due. One fully formed thought is better than a dozen fragments of unusable ideas.</p> <p>Be still. Breathe deeply and let your mind be at ease. Calmness and stillness allow you to examine your thoughts, not be overwhelmed by them.</p> <p>XIII</p> <p>Let your movements be precise. There are things you do everyday, do them well. Learn how to move efficiently and have a sense of control over your actions.</p> <p>Observe and improve your technique. Be adept at using your body. Find comfort in how well you perform daily activities. Get better at using your hands.</p> <p>XIV</p> <p>Be clean. Declutter your space, have good grooming and hygiene habits, smell good. How you look and how your space looks are a reflection of your inner life.</p> <p>Take the time to master this aspect of life as it has great impact on the quality of each lived moment. Living cleaner feels better, is healthier and essential to longevity.</p> <p>XV</p> <p>Don’t be a slave to your beliefs. There are countless ways to live. Do not judge others for having different beliefs and tastes than your own.</p> <p>Try to learn from different paths. Study the rituals and practices of the people of the world. Let your own beliefs become bizarre to you.</p> <p>Over the course of human history, we have created cultures and practices and ways of life in an effort to survive and thrive in the short time that we get to exist.</p> <p>Do not passively accept your prescribed way of life. Do what feels right. Act in accordance with your nature.</p> <p>XVI</p> <p>Improve your language. Our primary method of communication (self and otherwise) is through words. Expand your vocabulary to better describe your thoughts and state of being.</p> <p>Read more of the things that resonate with you. Write your thoughts out from time to time. Find your voice, your cadence, your choices of expression, your phrases.</p> <p>Don’t be afraid to mess with language. It is just noises and shapes to make sense of the world. Language neither was nor ever will be the same. The words we use today were once obsolete. One day they will be so again.</p> <p>If you can make yourself (or anyone) understand something with your language, it is fulfilling its purpose.</p> <p>XVII</p> <ol> <li>Life is short and unpredictable.</li> <li>Not everyone will like you.</li> <li>You can’t always get what you want.</li> <li>You can’t change the past.</li> <li>Life is filled with suffering.</li> <li>You are responsible for your own happiness.</li> <li>It’s ok to be wrong.</li> <li>You won’t always get what you deserve.</li> <li>You will make mistakes.</li> <li>Not everyone will agree with you.</li> </ol> <p>XVIII</p> <p>There are things beyond money that bring human beings fulfillment and meaning. I suppose this isn’t news to many, but hate it or love it, money is the religion of modernity. We need it for survival, we need it for our lives to have value in society. It’s a bitter pill of realization, but one we need to accept for the world isn’t going to change its mind about that anytime soon. That being said, it is easy to lose yourself in the pursuit of ever more capital gain. Many industries today proudly display the emblem of grind and hustle culture as a badge of honor and superiority. But our species didn’t evolve wanting to maximize utility. You’d be hard pressed to find someone truly well balanced and healthy that lives their life for money. Money should be used to buy time, not the other way around. Money can fulfill many of the desires a human being has. But capitalism distorts human nature. It is absurd to want to work most of your time being alive to accumulate things. Capitalism makes humans more individualistic and less cooperative. In my opinion, there is a way to balance your ability to make money and have a deeply fulfilling life. Find out what kind of work brings meaning and purpose to your life. It is easier to work a job that you are passionate about. Work with people you admire, work on things that tap into your talents and find joy in the successes you make on the job. Do things that bring you a deep sense of purpose and joy. Cooperate with people. Share ideas and don’t be afraid to defy norms. Love and respect people of all ilks. Money is important and necessary for survival. It is vital to living a good life. But living a life of purpose, depth and joy should be your ultimate focus. Do not sacrifice your humanity to become a cog in the neverending machine of work and growth. We get to be alive once, make it worthwhile.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="nonfic,"/><category term="advice,"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a personal perspective]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review - Prophet Song by Paul Lynch</title><link href="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/prophetsongReview/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review - Prophet Song by Paul Lynch"/><published>2024-04-12T16:21:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T16:21:00+00:00</updated><id>https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/prophetsongReview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/prophetsongReview/"><![CDATA[<p>4/12/24 <strong>Book Review: Prophet Song by Paul Lynch</strong></p> <p>Hmmmm Booker prize winner huh?<br/> I used to think that that meant something. I usually love Booker winners. Life of Pi, The White Tiger, The Seven Moons of Maali Almeida.</p> <p>This one was underwhelming. A story of civil war breaking out in Ireland from the perspective of a middle aged woman. Her naïveté and helplessness are frustrating and at times borderline psychotic. At one point she insists that the kids go to school when it’s clear that the city is being shelled and shot up.</p> <p>I also think the author wrote this as a means for white people to try and empathize with what’s actually happening to real human beings in other parts of the world by making it happen to someone that looks and thinks like them.</p> <p>The writing style is interesting. No paragraph breaks and no quotes for dialogue. And he loves metaphors. The plot is often brought to a grinding halt because he is quite impressed with himself for coming up with yet another way to compare Eilish’s inner turmoil to the cherry tree swaying in the dark outside. Regaining momentum often takes a few more pages, rinse and repeat.</p> <p>Some of the writing is truly beautiful, though. His understanding of love and grief and his way of alluding to behaviors rather than enunciating them was neat.</p> <p>Some highlights:</p> <p>“After a certain age, a man grows a beard not to enter manhood but to put a barrier to his youth”</p> <p>“he turns around and smiles without the smile reaching his eyes”</p> <p>“Larry’s muffled words reach upstairs and come shapeless into the room”</p> <p>“If you can change ownership of the institutions, you can change ownership of the facts”</p> <p>“Fear attracts the very thing it is afraid of,”</p> <p>“the dust laying itself down upon the years of their lives, the years of their lives slowly turning to dust”</p> <p>“We’ll no longer know who we are, I can’t conceive of myself as a person without the internet.”</p> <p>“Despising what she sees, the common run of mankind, what are they all but animals in docile servitude to the needs of body, tribe and state.”Hmmmm Booker prize winner huh?<br/> I used to think that that meant something. I usually love Booker winners. Life of Pi, The White Tiger, The Seven Moons of Maali Almeida.</p> <p>This one was underwhelming. A story of civil war breaking out in Ireland from the perspective of a middle aged woman. Her naïveté and helplessness are frustrating and at times borderline psychotic. At one point she insists that the kids go to school when it’s clear that the city is being shelled and shot up.</p> <p>I also think the author wrote this as a means for white people to try and empathize with what’s actually happening to real human beings in other parts of the world by making it happen to someone that looks and thinks like them.</p> <p>The writing style is interesting. No paragraph breaks and no quotes for dialogue. And he loves metaphors. The plot is often brought to a grinding halt because he is quite impressed with himself for coming up with yet another way to compare Eilish’s inner turmoil to the cherry tree swaying in the dark outside. Regaining momentum often takes a few more pages, rinse and repeat.</p> <p>Some of the writing is truly beautiful, though. His understanding of love and grief and his way of alluding to behaviors rather than enunciating them was neat.</p> <p>Some highlights:</p> <p>“After a certain age, a man grows a beard not to enter manhood but to put a barrier to his youth”</p> <p>“he turns around and smiles without the smile reaching his eyes”</p> <p>“Larry’s muffled words reach upstairs and come shapeless into the room”</p> <p>“If you can change ownership of the institutions, you can change ownership of the facts”</p> <p>“Fear attracts the very thing it is afraid of,”</p> <p>“the dust laying itself down upon the years of their lives, the years of their lives slowly turning to dust”</p> <p>“We’ll no longer know who we are, I can’t conceive of myself as a person without the internet.”</p> <p>“Despising what she sees, the common run of mankind, what are they all but animals in docile servitude to the needs of body, tribe and state.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="review,"/><category term="literature,"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[book review]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review - PTrust by Hernan Diaz</title><link href="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/trustreview/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review - PTrust by Hernan Diaz"/><published>2024-03-29T12:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-29T12:41:00+00:00</updated><id>https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/trustreview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2024/trustreview/"><![CDATA[<p>5/5</p> <p>A marvel of a novel. Unlike anything I’ve really read before. Layered with depth, dimension, emotion and an astute observation of capital and its imposing influence on narratives.</p> <p>The prose is elegant, yet the narrative has an addictively aggressive pace. It’s hard to find an author that can tow that remarkable line between literature and entertainment.</p> <p>As you go deeper into the meta fiction at play here, layers of meaning and truth are slowly uncovered and the reveals are utterly satisfying.</p> <p>Even the title is a clever play on the word Trust: in finance, in relationships, in narratives. And these aspects have been handled deftly and with nuance.</p> <p>I loved this read.</p> <p>Some highlights:</p> <p>“He became fascinated with the contortions of money-how it could be made to bend back upon itself to be force fed its own body”</p> <p>“she thought there was no greater violence than the one done to meaning”</p> <p>“she was quick to understand that he was very much impressed with Helen’s lineage and that he hoped to attach an old name to his new money.”</p> <p>“They doubt their right to hold someone else accountable for their happiness.”</p> <p>“And what is choice but a branch of the future grafting itself onto the stem of the present?”</p> <p>“Where perseverance and ingenuity once dwelled, apathy and despair now loiter.”</p> <p>“Every life is organized around a small number of events that either propel us or bring us to a grinding halt. We spend the years between these episodes benefiting or suffering from their consequences until the arrival of the next forceful moment.”</p> <p>“I have no country. I don’t want one. The root of all evil, the cause of every war - god and country.”</p> <p>“Authority and money surround themselves with silence, and one can measure the reach of someone’s influence by the thickness of the hush enveloping them.”</p> <p>“My job is about being right. Always. If I’m ever wrong, I must make use of all my means and resources to bend and align reality according to my mistake so that it ceases to be a mistake.”</p> <p>“That’s what they think friendship means: the freedom to turn you into a topic of conversation.”</p> <p>“For I’ve come to think one is truly married only when one is more committed to one’s vows than the person they refer to.”</p> <p>“Something miraculous and sad about the glass on the table. Water disciplined into a vertical cylinder. The depressing spectacle of our triumph over the elements.”</p> <p>“God is the most uninteresting answer to the most interesting questions.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="review,"/><category term="literature,"/><category term="personal"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[book review]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://salmanismustafa.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>